Hello everyone, welcome to this video.
In this video, we will be discussing
about Azure A agent framework workflows.
So far, we have discussed a lot about
how do we build chart based applications
using this particular framework.
However, you can also very well build
the agentic workflows using the same
framework. Unlike the traditional tools
that we use to build the workflows such
as SharePoint [gasps] using the Azure AI
agent framework, we can build the
intelligent workflows. For instance,
let's say you are part of a customer
support and based on the customer
request, you want to send the request to
the retention agent or to a
documentation specialist. So you will
first understand what exactly the user
it's asking for or looking for and based
on which you will route the request to
the corresponding team. So this workflow
can be automated using this framework so
that we can minimize the human workload.
Another example would be let's assume
that you wanted to automate the data
pipeline wherein like first of all you
need to read the news and like a
summarize and translate that news to a
different languages. So this can also be
done with this workflow. The another
sample like let's assume that we wanted
to support the software development life
cycle. So we will have a architect who
will you know go through the
specifications and like we will have a
developer who will implement that and
like we will have a security agent
performance agent or whoever is that
they will analyze the code and provide
the feedback to the developer and
developer will rectify all these
feedback. That's how like we can
completely automate the software
development life cycle. It uses the
model called direct graph. So direct
graph it's nothing but a mathematical
structure where like you will have a
nodes are connected by the edge. So if
you see here in this linear flow you
will have a input connected to the
process that connects to the output node
and you can also have a nonlinear flow
where like the developer node will be
writing some code and submit to the
reviewer. If a reviewer passes any
feedback, the developer needs to fix it
before the whole execution completes. So
using this direct graph model, you can
build both the linear and non nonlinear
flows. We know that Azure agent
framework it's enterprisegrade
implementation. It does provide a lot of
enterprise grade benefits. So to begin
with the observability using which you
should be able to understand every
single step during the execution
reliability let's assume that if during
the execution one node fails then you
should be able to catch that failure and
you know rerun that flow without
impacting the overall system and multi-
aent collaboration system as we
discussed here like there will be a
number of nodes. So you can always have
multiple agents like representing each
node right. So that in that sense like
you you in this workflow you will have a
multi- aent and persistent let's assume
that if you if you're running a long
running uh workflows for instance uh
user it's [clears throat] submitting for
a refund request and then like that
needs to be reviewed approved or
whatever is that or if you have that
kind of a longunning workflows you can
very well pause and resume the workflow.
Let's try to understand the overall
hierarchy. Here we will use the workflow
builder to build the workflow. Within
the workflow, we will have a number of
nodes. Each node will be represented
using the executor. Exeutor will be
having a number of handlers. So, think
of this way. Exeutor, it's a class. For
instance, this is a customer support.
The customer support will have a number
of tools. So, the handlers is nothing
but a tool that the customer support
will have it. Right? So like likewise
like this is going to be another node
say like a summarizer. So summarizer
will have its own tool and like this
entire workflow will be running in the
within that workflow runtime. Now let's
see how do we build a simple workflow
here. So if you see here first we are
initiating the builder as usual like if
you see this particular diagram we will
have a workflow builder. So we create a
instance of this particular builder.
Then we need a executor because like if
if for a workflow we need executor. So
we create executor and we define the
exeutor something this that. So the
executor name it's a greeting exeutor
extended from the uh you know default
exeutor class and it has two different
handlers. If you see here executor will
have a handler. So I have two handlers
here. So now we have a builder we have a
executor. Now we are saying that hey
builder set the start executor as this
particular exeutor. So because like say
like you have a number of exeutor you
need to tell the builder which is the
start executor and like from there like
you know we will be keep on adding the
edges to connect other executors. In
this workflow we will be having only one
node. So we just say just the start
executor and we call builder.build. So
that is going to give us the workflow
and we can run the workflow as simple as
that. Right? So now let's uh see the
detailed definition of each element. At
first we have executor. Executors are
nothing but a worker. Uh consider this
as a kind of a support engineer or a you
know client processing uh you know
engineer. So he is the person actually
you know can do a bit of a work for us
right. So that is what the executor and
then like a handler the engineer will
use the tools to perform action. So this
handler is nothing but a tool that the
executor can use it and typed message.
So this tool need to have some
information right. So the typed message
will pass that information or provide
that information to the tool or a
handler.
Then we have node. So when you have a uh
you know worker or executor
you wanted to keep them into the
workflow in order to do so you have to
create a node. So node is nothing but a
representation of a executor in the
workflow and edge it's what connects
multiple nodes together and workflow
builder it's what we use to build the
workflow and context like when we go
from one node to another node the
context it's what passed between these
nodes say like you have a you know node
A and node B from node A you wanted to
pass some information to node V you can
use this uh you know workflow context.
So the workflow context it's shared
across all the nodes. So everybody will
know the you know workflow context and
uh state and checkpoint let's say like
you are running a longunning workflow
uh in that sense like a checkpoint will
save the state of that particular
workflow later when you want to resume
that you know like where you left that
workflow from that point you can resume
that workflow.
If you know if if you understand all of
these then building a workflow will be
very simple. Now let's talk about some
of the core methods here. Uh first we
talk about the yield output. So as
mentioned here this is the final result
from the workflow. Whenever you wanted
to pass the final output from the
workflow you will be using the yield
output. uh at the same time like
whenever you want to send the message
between the nodes you will be using send
message and uh start executor it's like
when you build the workflow you have to
set what is your start executor from
which point it needs to workflow needs
to start and like add edges like when
you have the initial node from that
point you can say hey like from this
particular node you pass it to the next
node so like you can add multiple uh
nodes like connect multiple nodes
together.
[gasps] Now let's see like the type of
orchestrations. So first of all why do
we need a multi- aent orchestration?
So think of this way like instead of
building one big you know monolithic
agent
everybody will prefer the individual or
independent specialized workers and
that's how the enterprise operates right
and that's why like we need a multi-
aent orchestration and within the multi-
aent orchestration we do have you know
multiple patterns first we have a
sequential orchestration so name suggest
from one node to another node to another
node the you know flow it's very
sequential for instance like let's say
like the writer agent or you know
creates the draft and SEO agent optimize
that then finally it is reviewed by the
editor or like the data data entry agent
you know provides the information and
like that is reviewed by the risk
management risk and complaints right so
that's how it works it's so basically
like you know sequential [clears throat]
flow right then we have a concurrent
orchestration concurrent orchestration
like the task will be given to the uh
you know multiple teams at the very same
time and like we will be doing a
aggregation. So for instance like you
know like the market analysis the
sentiment agent the pricing agent and
the competitor agent will analyze
provide that information to the product
team uh to [clears throat] you know come
up with a final report or code review.
when you raise a PR the security agent
and the like performant agent the sale
agent all will review your PR and
provide the information right so that's
that's what we do with concurrent
orchestration uh group chart it's like
uh [clears throat] uh you know the
manager will receive the uh information
and like he will be collaborating with
the various uh teams he he is the one
who does the orchestration for us and
like a hand up uh it's like let's say
like you are working as a support
engineer in a support team. the lead
engineer will you know get to know your
uh incoming request and he will see like
what is that uh issue it's all about and
based on the you know type he will
assign the request to the support or a
take or a retain or whoever is that
right it's kind of a [clears throat] you
will have a you know leader who will
hand off the request to the specialized
team member then we have a magnetic
orchestration so basically it's pretty
similar to the group but then Here the
manager will make a you know back and
forth call between the agents right so
the difference between the group chart
and the magnetic orchestration uh group
chart the you know conversation it's
shared with everybody and everybody will
respond back to the manager at the same
time in magnetic uh orchestration the
manager will decide uh to whom to
interact with right so that is the only
difference between group chart and
magnetic. So basically like these are
all the patterns that we have but it
doesn't mean that these are all the only
patterns. It has the ability for us to
make or build our own pattern. Now with
that understanding let's go to the
visual studio code and try to execute
the workflows. I will try to cover all
the samples in two or three different
videos. We won't be able to cover
everything in this video. So before we
try to understand the code, we need to
understand the foundation here. I just
go back here one more time. So if you
see here, so this is how we build a
workflow, right? So if you see here like
we have a node executor, executor will
have a handler. So now let's go back
here. So there are two ways to define
the executor. You can use the uh
decorator based or a class-based.
Class-based we will uh look into the
next sample. But now let's focus on the
decorator one. So basically like what
you need to do is that you need to use
the decorator executor and provide id
and like you will be defining a
function. So I will come back to the
definition in a moment. But if you see
here I have two different executors. One
to handle the string one to handle the
number. So as usual like I try to build
a workflow using the workflow builder
and like this is my uh the initial
executor. I created the uh greeting
workflow. Now I try to run the workflow
by passing the string value get the
output and print the output. Right? So
now if I just come back here I just
print some information here you know
just to showcase hey like the workflow
works right. But then like in a real
world you will be doing your own
implementation here. So if you see here
we just print uh you know handling it
inside and like it just print a hello.
It takes a name and prints a hello and
uh it sends the me message. Now we are
using the yield output because like
there is no further node and this is the
single node workflow. So directly we are
sending the results back to the uh
workflow. Right now if you just see here
uh at the bottom we are again building
one more number builder workflow
and this uses the handle number as the
node here. So it is pretty similar to
the greeting workflow. uh instead it
just handles the number takes the number
right and it uh it it also returns the
value we print everything now if you see
here apart from the uh you know first
parameter we are also passing the
workflow context uh with that
understanding let's try to execute the
workflow it's a 27
AGF
uh executor
decorator based so now if you see here
we started the workflow by providing the
input as a cartic
that went inside the handler we just
printed this value here exactly that
matches and it says that I'm going to
send this value back to the workflow and
like in the output section we are
printing that value now what has
happened is that if you think of this
way like it has a it's a very tiny
workflow with one single node it takes
the input runs and prints the value
that's it right you can also build the
executor using the class so if you see
here in this program we are using the uh
class called greeting exeutor extended
from the executor. It has two different
handlers. Exactly the same handler
handles handle greeting handle number
similar to like what we had. If you see
here here we are using the executor
decorator but instead of that this is
part of a class called uh greeting
exeutor. Then we will create a instance
of that. Then we create a workflow using
the builder and we set that as the uh
initial node. Then we build our workflow
and we run it. So let's go ahead and run
this program here.
So the result it's exactly the same. The
only difference is that instead of using
the decorator executor decorator here we
are just using the class. So we need to
understand like what is the difference
between the executor and the class based
implementation. So if you just come over
here like whenever you wanted to build a
simple workflow or a kind of a prototype
you will go with the executor. But like
when you want to build enterprisegrade
workflows that most likely will be using
the class-based the reason is that the
decorator based one it's a stateless
where like the class-based one can be
stateful you can bring the state and it
is much easy for the third party
integration say like you have some
external integration so using the class
you should be able to do the integration
without you know uh much of effort. If
you look into this program, this clearly
demonstrate the capacity of the
class-based executors. So here like I'm
trying to create a support agent who
will handle the user message and the
system uh error code. So when user says
hey like something it's not working,
something it's low, the support agent
should be able to handle at the same
time it should also be able to handle
system related codes. say system throws
out of memory or high CPU usage related
codes it should be able to handle that
so now let's see like how do we use it
here right so now first we create a
agent uh then we create a builder here
and set that as a initial node here and
build the workflow in the first run the
user is saying hey I'm having trouble
with the login and like next the user
says hey my dashboard it's also not
working in the third run like we are
getting some system related code. So for
these two it should be able to call the
handle user message and you know able to
process that and like for the last one
for this one because this is a numerical
based one it should be able to make a
call to this particular uh handler here
and if you see here this is where like
we will be making the call to the
database for each user query we are just
you know storing that information and
retrieving that information into the
database here like I'm not really
connecting with the database but I'm
just saying that this is how we do it
right and this is how the class-based
executor supports the integration with
the third party component call it as a
database call it as a rest API or
anything you can very well integrate
using the executor so now let's you know
take a look into the private method so
you don't have to write everything into
the handler so what we can do is that
you can segregate or modularize is using
the private methods. So that's what we
do here. Right? So if you see here
exactly the same code but what I'm
saying here is that instead of writing
everything into the handler method I'm
creating some private methods so that I
can move my business logic outside of
the handler. So handler will receive the
input and then like it will make use of
the private method to execute the
business logic. Right? This will allow
us to follow all the design principles
that the enterprise enforces. So now
with that let's go ahead and run the
program. Let me clear the terminal.
Now if you see here the result it's
exactly the same. So the only difference
is that instead of writing everything
into the handler we just make use of the
private method. So this is the beauty of
using the class-based executor. Now I
hope you understand the difference
between the decorator based
implementation and a class-based
implementation. Again just to reiterate
the decorator based it's for a simple
workflows but like when you go with the
enterprise grade workflows you will end
up with the class-based exeutor. So
that's all I have for in this video. So
we'll continue to discuss all other
patterns in the following